# Diego Alburez-Gutierrez

Konrad-Zuse-Straße 1, 18057 Rostock, Germany alburezgutierrez@demogr.mpg.de; www.alburez.me

Diego (2019 Otto Hahn medalist) is a social scientist specialising in inter-generational demography. His work has used mathematical modeling, micro-simulation techniques, and empirical analysis to explore changes in the experience of life events such as kin availability, parental bereavement, and caring responsibilities.

### **EDUCATION**

## The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

PhD, Demography and Population Studies

2014 - 2018

- Summary: Effects of mass violence and genocide on population dynamics.
- Data collection: Genealogical surveys and in-depth interviews (1 year fieldwork)
- Mixed methods research design:
  - Quantitative analysis: Descriptive demographic, regression and survival models, network analysis
  - Qualitative analysis: Thematic and framework analysis
- Supervisors: Arjan Gjonça, Tiziana Leone, Ernestina Coast, and Michael Murphy

MSc, Social Research Methods (Distinction)

2013-2014

Practical approach with emphasis on quantitative and qualitative data analysis

## Del Valle University, Guatemala

BA, Anthropology (First class)

2008-2012

Thesis on evaluation methodologies for Conditional Cash Transfer Programmes

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany

Research Scientist (post-doc) and Research Area Chair (Aging and Generational Processes), Lab of Digital and Computational Demography

Since 2018

Leading role in projects using innovative data and approaches to understand demographic change in the context of global population aging.

# United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Denmark

Statistics Team Intern, Field Information and Coordination Support Section (FICSS) Central role in implementing UNHCR's Demographic Projection Tool.

2018

### control for impromonents of the formation for th

The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK Research Assistant, Law Department

2017

Leading qualitative research on low student satisfaction

Research Assistant, Social Policy Department

2016-2017

Quantitative analysis of maternal and child health outcomes in Palestine

Research Assistant, Sociology Department

2014-2015

Qualitative coding and analysis of methodological practices in sociology of work

Research Assistant, Methodology Department Survey of grey literature to identify common qualitative methods in International Development	2013-2014
Public Opinion Program, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala Lead researcher Designing and implementing qualitative research for the Media Monitoring Project	2013
<ul> <li>The Population Council, Guatemala</li> <li>Research Sub Coordinator</li> <li>Design and implementation of qualitative research on conditional cash transfer programmes</li> <li>Led team of four ethnographers during six months of data collection in rural Guatemala</li> </ul>	2012
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
European Doctoral School of Demography (EDSD), Barcelona Class Teacher for course "Digital Demography" Online due to COVID-19; materials and recorded lectures available on GitHub	2020
The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK  Class Teacher, Social Policy Department  • Leading seminars for the course "Introduction to Global Population Change"  • Weekly office hours, updated course website, homework and exam marking	2016-2017
<ul> <li>Class Teacher, LSE Methods Summer School</li> <li>Leading seminars for the "Qualitative Research Methods" strand</li> <li>Homework and exam marking</li> </ul>	2015
Del Valle University, Guatemala Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department	2013

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department

Leading seminars for the course "History of Anthropology 1"

2011

## OTHER PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Plaza Pública Newspaper, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala

• Leading seminars for the course "Advanced qualitative data analysis"

• Course design, wrote NVivo course pack (Spanish), homework and exam marking

Data journalist

2013

In charge of database management for data journalism focusing on local politics. Co-authored several publications.

## iDISC Information Technologies, Spain/Guatemala

Language moderator for translation of Microsoft Office 2013 to K'iche' Mayan

2012 - 2013

- In charge of recruitment, linguistics, and project management
- Led team of six translating the MS Office Language Interface Pack 2013 K'iche'

### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- Leone, T., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Gandour, R., Coast, E., and Giacaman, R. (2019). "Maternal and child access to care and intensity of conflict in the occupied Palestinian territory: a pseudo-longitudinal analysis (2000–2014)." Conflict and Health 13(1). doi:10.1186/s13031-019-0220-2.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (2019). Blood is thicker than bloodshed: A genealogical approach to reconstruct populations after armed conflicts. Demographic Research, 40(23): 627-656. doi:10.4054/DemRes.2019.40.23.
- McGovern, P., and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez**. (2017) "Who takes workplace case-study methods seriously? The influence of gender, academic rank and PhD training." Industrial Relations Journal 48(2):98-114, doi:10.1111/irj.12171.

### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

Alburez-Gutierrez, D., S. Aref, S. Gil-Clavel, A. Grow, D.V. Negraia, E. Zagheni. (2019). "Demography in the Digital Era: New Data Sources for Population Research." Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the Italian Statistical Society. doi: 10.31235/osf.io/24jp7.

#### TECHNICAL REPORTS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** and Segura Garcia, C. (2018). "The UNHCR Demographic Projection Tool: estimating the future size and composition of forcibly displaced populations." UNHCR Statistics Technical Series, 2018/1.

## WORKING PAPERS AND PAPERS IN PROGRESS

- **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, E. Zagheni and M. Kolk. (November 2019) "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective". SocArxiv. doi: 10.31235/osf.io/s69fz.
- Smith-Greenway, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Zagheni, E. and Trinitapoli, J. (in progress) "Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: A Worldwide Analysis of Maternal Cumulative Prevalence of Child Mortality".
- Williams, I. and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez** (in progress) "A formal demographic approach to child survival from a mother's perspective: mortality change and related measures".
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (April 2020). "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala".
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (January 2020). "Fertility and pronatalism among massacre survivors in Mayan Guatemala".

- Statistical programming: R (base, tidyverse, data.table, parallel, shiny), Stata, Excel
- Text processing and web: IATEX, MS Office, (r)markdown, HTML, JavaScript, Tesseract
- Other programming: Git, Python 3, SQL, Hadoop
- Demographic microsimulation: SOCSIM with applications in R
- Qualitative data analysis: NVivo, Atlas.ti
- Experience in qualitative, quantitative, and online data collection

### **LANGUAGES**

- International: **Spanish** (native), **English** (full professional C2), **German** (full professional C1), **Swedish** (beginner A1)
- Guatemalan/Mexican: **K'iche'** (full professional C1), **Achi** (full professional C1), **Kaqchikel** (professional B1), **Q'eqchi'** (limited working A2)

### SERVICE TO THE DISCIPLINE

- Reviewer for academic journals: Demography, Journal of Marriage and Family, Demographic Research, Revue Quetelet/Quetelet Journal
- Organiser Workshop: Demographic Research with Web and Social Media Data, International Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), Munich 2019
- Expert witness for US asylum cases at the 'Center for Gender & Refugee Studies' Since 2018
- Organiser of the 'Social Policy Qualitative Research Group', London School of Economics 2017-2018
- President of the 'Methodology Society', London School of Economics 2013-2014
- President of the 'Social Sciences Union', Del Valle University (Guatemala) 2011-2012

### SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

- Otto Hahn Medal (2019) awarded by the Max Planck Society for 'outstanding achievement from the initial creative period of young scientists'
- LSE PhD Academy Prize (2018) for research on state-sponsored massacres in Guatemala
- LSE PhD Studentship (2014-2018)

### PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP)
- British Society for Population Studies (BSPS)
- Population Association of America (PAA)
- Latin American Studies Association (LASA)
- Households in Conflict Network (HiCN)
- International Science, Technology, and Innovation Network of Guatemala (REDCTI)

# SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

- Academic video: 'How Can We Quantify the Immediate and Lingering Impact of Genocide on Local Populations?' (Latest Thinking, Apr 2020)
- Opinion piece about need for COVID-19 testing in Latin America (The Conversation, UK, Apr 2020)